A Guide to the Papers of Thomas Allibone Janvier, 1844-1902
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Thomas Allibone Janvier 1844-1902
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7746
32 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was deposited by Clifton Waller Barrett on December 17, 1963, accessioned on November 18, 1964, and changed to a gift on July 1, 1991.
Scope and Content
This collections consists of 32 items, chiefly correspondence and manuscript of Thomas Allibone Janvier.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in three series. Series I consists of manuscripts, Series II consists of correspondence, and Series III consists of miscellaneous material.
Contents List
- Series I: Manuscripts
  - The Roses of Monsieur Alphonse n.d., AMsS, 79p.
    Bound volume, blue cloth binding, title page: "The Roses of Monsieur Alphonse/Final Draft," bound in is portrait print of author.
  - Gull Island Light n.d., AMsS, 22p.
    Each leaf mounted on a sheet (back and front) in blue exercise book, autograph of William E. Barton on first page.
- Series II: Correspondence
  - Francis de Haes Janvier to Rev. R. W. Griswold 1844 Mar 29, ALS, 2p.
    Sends letter by Dr. Hooker, mentions that he has been in New York for two weeks and where he is living, asks Griswold to visit.
  - Francis de Haes Janvier to Rev. R. W. Griswold 1847 Nov 24, ALS, 3p.
    Mentions Griswold's controversy with Headley, reminds Griswold of his promise to see that Hooker's book is noticed in New York papers, encloses article by Dr. Ducachet, asks Griswold to come to see him in Philadelphia.
  - John Jay to Justin Winsor 1888 Feb 29, ALS, 1p.
    Returns proof, asks that he not omit Fitzmaurice map, as it is valuable for showing "what France proposed for us."
  - Thomas Allibone Janvier to Mr. Stoddart 1889 Jun 12, ALS, 2p.
    Gives Stoddart Mrs. Harris' address and tells him when she will be at home, mentions that her books have sold well, says Stoddart does not owe him thanks because he is returning favors Stoddart did for him in the past, asks him to stop by for breakfast and to see Spanish books.
  - Thomas Allibone Janvier to Clarence Clough Buel 1889, ALS, 1p.
    Does not want to trouble Buel for typewritten copy of "San Antonio of the Gardens" as he expects to have a proof of it within six weeks as a part of Stedman's book of his writings.
  - Thomas Allibone Janvier to Seeger 1891 May 25, ALS, 2p.
    Having learned that Seeger has gone to Mexico, jokes about profit the can make by writing guidebooks about Mexico, mentions Seeger's export business.
  - Thomas Allibone Janvier to William Thomas Smedley 1892 Jan 19, ALS, 2p.
    Wants Smedley to send his New York address so that he can send "Madame" a gift.
  - Thomas Allibone Janvier to Robert Underwood Johnson 1894 Jun 1, ALS, 2p.
    Wants $40 per thousand words instead of the $30 offered by Johnson, but will accept $30 if necessary, because of his "strong desire" to have his articles in Century, mentions Buel and Gilder, penciled notes in unidentified hand, express shock at the cost.
  - Thomas Allibone Janvier to Robert Underwood Johnson 1894 Jul 8, ALS, 2p.
    Glad that he will be permitted to do certain articles for Century, thanks Johnson for his encouraging words, mentions working with [Andre] Castaigue.
  - Robert Underwood Johnson to W. C. 1895 May 21, ANS.
    "Cable Janvier" suffering for Rhone article ( A Feast-day on the Rhone? ).
  - Thomas Allibone Janvier to Richard Watson Gilder 1896 Jun 7, ALS, 6p.
    Writes about an article he is working on for the Christmas issue of a magazine [unnamed], wants more space in the magazine than he has been allotted.
  - homas Allibone Janvier to Messrs. Osgood, McIlvaine & Co. 1896 Aug 27, ALS, 1p.
    Received check for royalties due, asks that note be made of his correct address.
  - Thomas Allibone Janvier to Richard Watson Gilder 1896 Aug 27, ALS, 1p.
    Announces Christmas article almost finished and will send it in a week to New York, article required much work, hopes he will be paid accordingly.
  - Thomas Allibone Janvier to Richard Watson Gilder 1896 Aug 30, ALS, 1p.
    Janvier is sick, hoping to recover quickly.
  - Thomas Allibone Janvier to Richard Watson Gilder 1896 Sep 14, ALS, 3p.
    Sending article on the Christmas customs of Provence, article too long but can be edited by Richard Watson Gilder; hopes it can be used in entirety; asks payment be sent quickly, as he is "in dire poverty," request to cable him (in France) if Richard Watson Gilder likes article.
  - Thomas Allibone Janvier to Richard Watson Gilder 1896 Sep 15, ALS, 2p.
    Received Richard Watson Gilder's telegram just after mailing manuscript, hopes it arrives in time, apologizes in case it is late.
  - Thomas Allibone Janvier to Richard Watson Gilder 1897 Mar 31, ALS, 2p.
    Thanks Richard Watson Gilder for notifying him of decision by telegraph, sorry Richard Watson Gilder cannot use Mexican story, asks Richard Watson Gilder to send the manuscript to brother F. H. Janvier in Philadelphia, is going to London in six weeks, asks Richard Watson Gilder to come to London for Queen's Jubilee.
  - Thomas Allibone Janvier to Richard Watson Gilder 1899 Jan 27, ALS, 2p.
    Writing an article about nativity plays in Provence for Century 's Christmas issue, thanks for new volume of Richard Watson Gilder's poems sent by Helena.
  - Thomas Allibone Janvier to Richard Watson Gilder 1899 Mar 8, ALS, 1p.
    Assumes Richard Watson Gilder not interested in nativity plays of Provence since Gilder has not answered previous letter [1899 Jan 27], so has stopped work on article.
  - Thomas Allibone Janvier to Richard Watson Gilder 1899 Mar 29, ALS, 3p.
    Protest cuts Richard Watson Gilder has made in his article about Christmas customs, suggest another way of presenting material, asks for prompt answer.
  - Thomas Allibone Janvier to Richard Watson Gilder 1899 Jun 8, ALS, 2p.
    Sending by registered mail "A Provencal Postscript," complains about Richard Watson Gilder's editing, suggest a certain photograph be used as illustration; penciled note by Richard Watson Gilder.
  - Thomas Allibone Janvier to Richard Watson Gilder 1899 Sep 27, ALS, 1p.
    Thanks for payment for "Christmas thing," he may have to return the check for correction as it was written to S. A. Janvier, taking a holiday on the Kent coast, sending corrected proof.
  - Thomas Allibone Janvier to Mrs. Morris P. [?] 1901 Feb 17, ALS, 2p.
    Apologizes for delay in answering note, had been out of country and servants (of the Century Association) failed to forward her note, only book he had published about New York is in In Old New York, Harper's Magazine published three articles about old-time shipping in New York.
  - Thomas Allibone Janvier to Richard Watson Gilder 1902 Jul 9, ALS, 1p.
    Sorry Richard Watson Gilder cannot use "The Convent of the Little Bells," but appreciates nice letter; very busy working on Christmas story and article about old New York, so cannot write text to go with Langren's pictures of London, suggests they do not need a text, just a word or two of explanation.
  - Thomas Allibone Janvier to Richard Watson Gilder Jan 24, ALS, 2p.
    Not many Americans interested in the Felibres, mentions French poets who were Felibres: Frederic Mistral, Joseph Roumanille, Theodore Aubanel, mentions Cauouge and Bigot.
  - Thomas Allibone Janvier to Richard Watson Gilder Jul 20, ALS, 1p.
    Asks Richard Watson Gilder to send copy of his article on Rouuer [?] if Gilder approves the use of it as an introduction of the American edition of the new book, mentions Mr. Scott, Lythoff, Leiden.
  - Thomas Allibone Janvier to Clarence Clough Buel (?) Jul 28, ALS, 2p.
    Mentions a proof he is returning, asks Buel to send the revised work to him so he can send it to publisher in Holland, wishes he could take a cruise with Buel, asks him to bring boat "here" (Narrangansett, R.I.), hopes in the fall to spring upon Buel and "agreeable surprise."
  - Thomas Allibone Janvier to Jenkins Aug 10, ALS, 1p.
    Asks Jenkins send him three copies of Hillier's article from today's paper, wants to send them to Hillier's people in England, congratulates Jenkins and says he will "make the next president," mentions Nagle.
  - Thomas Allibone Janvier to Robert Bridges n.d., ALS, 2p. on 1 l.
    Humorous acceptance of invitation to "tell a story" to a club [Aldine Club?].
- Series III: Miscellaneous
  - Copy of note made by Janvier n.d., 2p.
    Mentions de Lairesse (Flemish Artist), Groot Schilderbock, "Andres del Sarto" (poem) and "Fra Lippo Lippi" (poem), (ALSS note: Robert Browning Parleying?).